Finding Aid for Research Club (University of Michigan) records, 1900-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Research Club (University of Michigan) records 1900-1990
University of Michigan. Research Club.
87305 Bimu M1 2
Constitution, history, minutes of council and regular meetings, membership materials, and programs.
4 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (Donor No. 1286 ) has been received in several accessions. The most recent accession (Donor No. 587) was received in March 2001.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Research Club of the University of Michigan was founded in 1900 as the "Society for Promotion of Research at the University of Michigan." In its constitution, adopted on February 15, 1900, the club first articulated its goal: "to unite those members of the academic staff of the university who are actively engaged in research, and to originate and support such measures as are calculated to foster and advance research in the university."
According to W.H. Hobb's history of the Research Club, the Research Club was the brainchild of Drs. Frederick C. Newcombe and Jacob E. Reighard; and the first meeting of the club was held at the home of Dr. Victor C. Vaughn on January 6, 1900, with four others present.
Sixteen charter members elected Vaughn as the club's first president. Membership required nomination by two current Research Club members, and a subsequent ballot by a committee of eight, with one dissenting vote excluding a nominee from membership. Current membership goes through one of five divisional selection committees that then present nominees to the Council.
From the beginning, the organization excluded women, who organized their own Women's Research Club in October of 1902. A separate Junior Research Club (later called the Science Research Club) for younger faculty members was also established in October of 1902.
The Research Club has typically held monthly meetings during the academic year, with two faculty members presenting on their research projects. The club has also supported the research of graduate students, sponsoring since 1933 monetary loans and then grants for dissertation research.
When the Henry Russel Lectureship was established by endowment in 1925, the Regents of the University delegated responsibility for the selection of the annual lecturer to the Executive Board of the Research Club, and the Research Club maintains that responsibility.
The records of the Research Club date from the organization's inception in 1900 through 1990 and include minutes, membership materials and meeting records. The records are divided into three series: Organizational, Meetings, and Membership.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Research Club.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Research.
- Organizational
  The Organizational series (1900-1990, 1.0 linear ft.) contains the governing documents of the Research Club, including the constitution with its changes over time, various histories of the organization, listings of officers, treasurer's reports, and background information on the Research Club's role in the selection of the Henry Russel Lectureship. This series gives the researcher a basic understanding of the governance and leadership of the Research Club over time. For more information about the Henry Russel Lecture, see the separate collection.
  - 25th Anniversary 1925 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Publications Report 1921 (Box 1)
  - Commemorative lists 1965-1986 (Box 1)
  - Constitution (1900) with meeting minutes (1900-1907) and membership list, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Constitution (1904) with meeting minutes 1907-1913, 1 volumes (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, bylaws, records summaries 1900-1990 (1900 and 1904 constitutions in bound volume in box 2) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Reports 1907-1936 (Box 1)
    - 1938-1940, 1946-1951 (Box 1)
    - 1952-1954 (Box 1)
    - 1962-1973 (Box 1)
    - 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - 1977-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Dues notices 1970-1979, 1986 (Box 1)
  - Elections 1972-1976, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Finances 1950-1973 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Scholarship 1950, 1962, 1973-1974, 1985 (Box 1)
  - History of the Research Club 1900-1937 (W. H. Hobbs) (Box 1)
  - History of the Research Club 1900-1950 (Edward H. Kraus) (Box 1)
  - History of the Research Club 1900-1913 (Warren P. Lombard) (Box 1)
  - Insurance 1986 (Box 1)
  - Lombard notes, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Mailing lists 1932-1946, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes on the club 1900-1925 (Box 1)
  - Officers, councilors, committee chairs listings 1900-1979 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Responsibilities 1972-1984 (Box 1)
  - Russel Lectures
    - Call for nominations 1986-1990 (Box 1)
    - History 1945, 1957, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Selection committee 1961-1990 (Box 1)
    - Selection procedure 1941-1989 (Box 1)
  - Secretarial Responsibilities 1940 (Box 1)
  - Treasurer's reports 1948-1989 (Box 1)
  - Various reports 1909-1925 (Box 1)
  - Women's Research Club 1939, 1972, 1978 (Box 1)
- Meetings
  - Lists of programs 1900-1982 (Box 2)
  - Lists of research projects 1928 (Box 2)
  - Memorial meetings 1909-1975 (Box 2)
  - Minutes 1900-1990
    The Meetings series (1900-1990, 0.8 linear ft.) contains programs and notices of nearly every regular and Council meeting for the Research Club since its inception. These programs list speakers and topics for each meeting, providing a contemporaneous look at the life of the organization and areas of faculty research. The minutes of the Council board and of the regular meetings provide a detailed understanding of the organization's processes and policies.
    - Board Meetings
      - 1913-1924 (Box 2)
      - 1924-1928 (Box 2)
      - 1928-1932 (Box 2)
      - 1932-1936 (Box 2)
      - 1936-1941 (Box 2)
      - 1941-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1944-1948 (Box 2)
      - 1948-1952 (Box 2)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 2)
      - 1965-1979 (Box 2)
    - Regular Meetings
      - 1900-1907 with constitution (1900) and membership list, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - 1907-1913 with 1904 constitution, 1 volumes (Box 2)
      - 1913-1923 (Box 2)
      - 1928-1932 (Box 2)
      - 1933-1936 (Box 2)
      - 1936-1941 (Box 2)
      - 1941-1944 (Box 2)
      - 1944-1948 (Box 2)
      - 1948-1962 (Box 2)
      - 1963-1970 (Box 2)
  - Programs
    - 1924-1940 (Box 2)
    - 1942-1956 (Box 2)
    - 1960-1990 (Box 2)
- Membership
  The Membership series (1900-1990, 2.2 linear ft.) details policies for membership and includes member lists and a substantial number of original nominations for membership (including CVs). Through the membership series, the researcher can follow the growth of the Research Club through time and understand the membership selection process.
  - Former members 1940-1944 (Box 2)
  - Guest members 1937-1942 (Box 2)
  - Guidelines for membership 1912 1971-78 (Box 2)
  - Life members 1971-1974 (Box 2)
  - Membership committees 1970-1975 (Box 2)
  - Membership lists
    - 1905-1921 (Box 2)
    - 1921-1925 (Box 2)
    - 1948-1964 (Box 2)
    - 1966-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Membership list with titles of presentations 1900-1925 (Box 3)
  - Membership reports on candidates 1951-1989 (Box 3)
  - Membership update 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Memorials to members 1915-1927 (Box 3)
  - Postponed nominations 1936-1943 (Box 3)
  - Recommendations for new members circa 1955, 1981 (Box 3)
  - Unsuccessful candidates 1936-1943 (Box 3)
  - Members
    - A (Box 3)
    - B-Bernstein (Box 3)
    - Bethell-Burt (Box 3)
    - Ca-Co (Box 3)
    - Cr-Cu (Box 3)
    - Da-Di (Box 3)
    - Do-Du (Box 3)
    - E (Box 3)
    - F (Box 3)
    - G-Goldberg (Box 3)
    - Gomberg-Guthe (Box 3)
    - Ha (Box 3)
    - He-Ho (Box 3)
    - Hu-Hy (Box 3)
    - I-J (Box 3)
    - K-Kikuchi (Box 3)
    - Kilgour-Kurath (Box 4)
    - L (Box 4)
    - M-Meech (Box 4)
    - Meinke-Myers (Box 4)
    - N-O (Box 4)
    - P-Peckham (Box 4)
    - Pedley-Pulgram [Q] (Box 4)
    - R (Box 4)
    - S-Sleaton (Box 4)
    - Smith-Stason (Box 4)
    - Steenrod-Swanson (Box 4)
    - T (Box 4)
    - U-V (Box 4)
    - W-White (Box 4)
    - Whitehall-Z (Box 4)
  - Card file of club members and papers read (Box 4)